Okay, so again כ״ז עמוד ב׳ Chaf Zayin Amud Bet where it
says let's read it one more time for רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה.
Reb Yossi b'Reb Yehuda. So for רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Reb Yossi
b'Reb Yehuda about eight lines from the bottom, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
האי בת אשת אביך מאי עביד ליה? Reb Yossi b'Reb Yehuda hai
bat eshet avicha mai avid lei? What does רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Reb Yossi b'Reb Yehuda do with the prohibition of why the verse
says the daughter of your father's wife, if according to him there
is only one prohibition of sister regardless of whether your father was
married to your sister's mother or not? So why does the verse
have a, why is there a need for an additional verse that
speaks about the daughter of your father's wife? So what does he
do with that verse? מיבעי ליה Miba'ei lei and this is why
we brought this whole thing in, מי שיש לו אישות לאביך. mi
sheyesh lo ishus le'avicha. The only person who is considered to be
your sister halachically is a woman who marriage is possible with your
father.
אישות לאביך Ishus le'avicha פרט לאחותו משפחה ועכו״ם perat l'achoiso mi'shifcha ve'akum
to exclude your sister that derives
from a that comes from either a slave or a non-Jewish woman
שאין אישות לאביך בה she'ein ishus le'avicha bah that your father cannot
have and marriage is not possible and therefore she is not defined
as your sister. So this was the point of bringing the whole
discussion of a sister and is there another prohibition of daughter of
father's wife to get to this פסוק pasuk and to רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה Reb Yossi b'Reb Yehuda who learns from this that someone
is only considered a sister if she comes from a woman that
your father could have married and that the child of a non-Jewish
woman or the child of a female slave is not considered to
be a person's child, legally is not legally a person's child. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואימא פרט לאחותו ve'aima perat l'achoiso so that
is true that it is excluded because there is no marriage with
such a woman. There is a lot of other people we could
have included in that category. So first of all the גמרא Gemara
says ואימא פרט לאחותו מאנוסה. ve'aima perat l'achoiso me'anusa. How about a
woman that just happens not to be married to your father? Marriage
is possible but happens not to be? That would sort of be
how
in general in larger society a bastard is a child that is
born from somebody who is not a man's legal wife. And so
maybe that and that is not a person's legal kid. So maybe
a child from a woman who is not the father's wife is
not considered a legal child? So again the גמרא Gemara also using
the case of אנוסה, anusa, rape, rather than other cases like מפותה
mefuta which we have mentioned before is problematic. But anyway ההיא לא
מצית אמרת. hahi lo matzit amrit. You cannot say this. You cannot
say a child from someone who is not a wife is not
legally a child. מדרבא Mid'Rava from רבא. Rava. דרבא רמי. D'Rava rami.
רבא Rava shows a contradiction. כתיב Ketiv one verse says ערות בת
בנך או בת בתך לא תגלה. ervat bat bincha o bat bitecha
lo tegaleh. So it says do not reveal the nakedness your granddaughter,
your son's daughter or your daughter's daughter. הבת בנך דידך ובת בתך
דידך Habat bincha didach u'bat bitecha didach which suggests and it emphasizes
your granddaughter that if it is just your wife's granddaughter and not
your own so שרי shari it would be permissible. וכתיב U'chetiv but
another verse says ערות אשה ובתה לא תגלה. ervat isha u'vitah lo
tegaleh. Do not reveal the nakedness of a woman and her daughter
את בת בנה ואת בת בתה et bat b'nah v'et bat bitah
or her granddaughter. So one verse says your granddaughter, the other verse
says her granddaughter. Now it is not exactly clear to me why
this is such a problem because a lot of verses prohibit a
lot of things. But somehow
the גמרא Gemara feels that this is that the first verse suggests
not her granddaughter and here it says yes her granddaughter. הא כיצד?
Ha keitzad? How do you reconcile it? כאן באונסין כאן בנשואין. Kan
be'onsin, kan benissuin. It depends whether again rape, which is always the
phrase the גמרא Gemara uses when it talks about non-marital, again
do not know why it is always going to the rape case,
and the other is the case of marital. So if you are
married to the woman then you cannot have sex with her granddaughter.
But if you are not married to the woman then her granddaughter
is not a problem, it is
only if it is your granddaughter that is a problem.
Now man is sleeping with a woman he is not married to.
If she has a granddaughter that is not his, not a problem.
But a granddaughter that is his with this woman is a problem.
So it says ah, you see that a child that comes from
a non-marriage situation, this man is sleeping with this woman he is
not married to, the child is still his and the granddaughter is
still considered his. So if somebody is considered to be a legal
child even not in the context of marriage then presumably if that
is true about this man's child it would also be true that
it would be somebody's sister or somebody's brother. Is that clear? Meaning
the suggestion is how do we know this idea that somebody is
not, this is not the ממזר mamzer question. This is the question
about not a legal child, it is not considered to be a
legal child. Again in English we tend to think bastard that is
what it means, not a legal child, and we tend to say
that it comes outside of the context of when it is born
not in the context of marriage. context to have a legal marriage.
But that's not halachically. Halachically, that's the point of this משנה. mishna.
Any brother מכל מקום, mi kol makom, child מכל מקום, mi kol
makom, even ממזר, mamzer, even whatever, it's all considered to be somebody's
legal child with the exception of the child of a שפחה shifcha
and a non-Jewish woman. So the גמרא Gemara says, well how do
you know? If it's based on the fact that there can't be
marriage with a שפחה shifcha or non-Jewish woman, maybe we should say
any child that results from a union that was conceived outside of
wedlock? So the גמרא Gemara says, it's not true. Since we know
that there's a prohibition of עריות arayos with a grandchild that resulted
from a non-wedlock situation, right? So therefore, clearly somebody is still considered
a legal child when they result from a non-wedlock situation. And if
that's true, would also be considered a legal sibling. So we cannot
just say that anybody born out of wedlock is not considered a
child. So then the גמרא Gemara says, top of כ"ג עמוד א',
chaf gimmel amud aleph, ואימא פרט לחייבי לאוין. ve-eima p'rat le-chayvei lavin.
Okay,
but fine, so you want to say it's just that it happens
to be out of wedlock. But there's maybe it's things that women
you're not allowed to marry even
if any type of a union that was not legal, the child
shouldn't be a legal child. So for example a woman that's just
prohibited by a negative prohibition. Like let's say a גרושה grusha to
a כהן, kohen, or a case of a ממזרת mamzeres or a
ממזר. mamzer. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, חייבי לאוין תפסי בהו
קידושין. chayvei lavin tafsei behu kiddushin. No. We know that and this
is what we've been saying all along, that marriage is binding between
in a union that is prohibited just by a simple negative prohibition.
Marriage is only not binding if it's a union that is כרת,
kares, but a union that's a simple negative prohibition, like the prohibitions
of a כהן kohen or cases of let's say
ממזר, mamzer, or שפחה, shifcha, those cases marriage is binding. And since
marriage is binding, it is therefore it would not be categorically different
than other cases where maybe there is even when there isn't marriage,
we said that the child is considered a legal child. So here
too, even if it's prohibited, since marriage is possible and would be
binding if it happened, the child would be a legal child. Now
how do we know that marriage is binding in this case? דכתיב,
dichtiv, כי תהיין לאיש שתי נשים, ki tiheina le-ish shtei nashim, if
a man has two wives, אחת אהובה ואחת שנואה, achas ahuvah ve-achas
snuah, one beloved and one hated. וכי יש אהובה לפני המקום ויש
שנואה לפני המקום? ve-chi yesh ahuvah lifnei HaMakom ve-yesh snuah lifnei HaMakom?
So the גמרא Gemara asks a funny question because the point in
the פסוק pasuk here is this man doesn't want this, doesn't like
this wife and therefore he wants to disinherit the son. But the
גמרא Gemara assumes that obviously just because he wanted
to disinherit, that wouldn't give a legal basis for it. So it
assumes that maybe the point of the פסוק pasuk is to tell
you a חידוש, chiddush, that even though there's some objective way the
woman is less desired and less appropriate, maybe and that should be
the basis for disinheriting the son. So what would that be? Is
there any woman who is not beloved before God? וכי יש אהובה
לפני המקום ויש שנואה לפני המקום? ve-chi yesh ahuvah lifnei HaMakom ve-yesh
snuah lifnei HaMakom? אלא אהובה אהובה בנישואיה שנואה שנואה בנישואיה. ella ahuvah
ahuvah b'nisueha snuah snuah b'nisueha. Yes, it means one is beloved in
the marriage, meaning it's a legitimate marriage, and the other is hated
in the marriage. Not again about the man's feelings for her, but
that the marriage should not have taken place. Why? Because there was
a negative prohibition, so the marriage should not have taken place. ואמר
רחמנא, ve-amar Rachmana, so that's the scenario. So it wants to make
a bigger חידוש chiddush in the פסוק. pasuk. It's not just that
a man doesn't like his wife and wants to disinherit. There's a
reason that the woman should be and her child should be considered
less entitled. Because they weren't supposed to have been married this man,
there was a negative prohibition.
And nevertheless, ואמר רחמנא ve-amar Rachmana כי תהיין, ki tiheina, if this
woman belongs to this man,
meaning הוויה, havayah, the word to be, the גמרא Gemara understands that
that means that is referred to in the context of marriage. כי
תהיין לאיש שתי נשים, ki tiheina le-ish shtei nashim, he's married to
these two women. So you see that even a case where it's
prohibited by a negative prohibition,
that's the דרשה. drasha. So that is the minimum case that something
is not a non-acceptable marriage. Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara is telling you
that the marriage is binding. So what we have is the following.
We have that somebody born from a woman that marriage is not
possible with is not a person's legal son. So the גמרא Gemara
says, well maybe it just means that marriage didn't happen to take
place with a normal woman just out of wedlock. It says that
can't be, because we know within the world of עריות, arayos, a
child born out of wedlock is still considered a child. Like a
person's granddaughter out of wedlock is still a granddaughter and so on.
So out of wedlock doesn't change the status. Okay, says the גמרא,
Gemara, but maybe still maybe it's things that marriage is prohibited and
it's like a simple לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. And the גמרא Gemara
says no, the concept is that marriage isn't once we say out
of wedlock doesn't matter, then the next category you go to is
that wedlock is not even possible. It's excluded from the category of
wedlock. Somehow just being prohibited would not have been enough to change
the possible status of the child. So the next place to move
if you say out of wedlock doesn't change the status would be
wedlock is not possible, not just that the act is prohibited. And
therefore simple negative prohibitions do not create a non-legitimate. child, because there
marriage is possible, marriage is binding. Of course the next stage is,
okay fine, but there's another category before you get to a non-Jewish
woman that marriage is impossible, marriage isn't binding, which is not just
a negative prohibition, but everything we've been talking about, the איסורי כרת,
issurei kares, all of the weightier, you know, עריות, arayos, marriage isn't
binding. So if a man goes ahead and has sex with a
married woman, or has sex with his aunt, or his sister, all
those things that produce ממזר, mamzer, that's not just that it happened
to be out of marriage, that's not just that it's prohibited, that
actually is a case in which marriage isn't, wouldn't even be binding
at all. So if that's the logic, a child that is produced
from a union in which marriage is not possible, then every case
of a ממזר mamzer essentially should also be a person's non-legitimate child,
not just ממזר. mamzer. ממזר mamzer means the child can't marry somebody
else, but still it's a legitimate child in the sense about inherit
him, you know, all of the legal statuses of child and sibling
or whatever, that's our משנה mishnah applied by ממזר. mamzer. And this
is what the גמרא gemara is asking, why should that be? So
let's take a look. ואימא, ve'eima, so why don't we say פרט
לחייבי כריתות? prat lechayvei kerisos? Fine, it exclude people that cases in
which the union is prohibited by כרת, kares, where the union is
where marriage is impossible at all. So let's say the child from
that union is not only a ממזר mamzer but not a person's
legal child. So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so says Rava, אמר קרא,
amar kra, the verse says, ערבת אחותך בת אביך בת אמך מולדת
בית או מולדת חוץ. Ervat achosecha bat avicha bat imecha moledes bayis
o moledes chutz.
The nakedness of your sister, your daughter, your father's daughter, your mother's
daughter, whether born in the house or outside. So what does that
mean, in the house or outside? בין שאומרים לו לאביך קיים בין
שאומרים לו לאביך הוצא, Bein she'omrim lo le'avicha kayem bein she'omrim lo
le'avicha hotze, whether they tell your father keep your wife, or whether
they tell your father get rid of your wife,
meaning even if it's in the case where he's married to a
ערוה, ervah, the offspring,
the child that results is still considered to be your sister, דאמר
רחמנא אחותך היא, de'amar rachmana achosechi hi,
your sister. Okay now, it's not exactly clear to me that again
maybe that's just a case of לאו, lav, how do you know
it's a case of כרת? kares? But you could say that we
already addressed the case of לאו lav before, so this is going
one step further to address the case of כרת. kares. Also maybe
the idea of אומרים לו לאביך הוצא, omrim lo le'avicha hotze, get
rid of her, you know, divorce her, well again you could go
both ways, you could say if he needs to divorce her it
shows that the marriage is binding, but maybe the point that the
גמרא gemara is saying is הוצא hotze meaning that the even in
a case where there's no marriage at all, that the marriage isn't
binding at all, like it's איסור כרת, issur kares, nevertheless the child
that results is still considered to be your sister. Okay so that's
what it learns from מולדת חוץ, moledes chutz, even born from a
union that was that was not even able a woman who was
not able to even be in the house as it were, a
woman that marriage wasn't binding with, nevertheless the child still is the
man's legal child and therefore your sister. Yes.
I embarrassingly have forgotten, what are we in other words the the
offspring of a slave or of a pagan woman?
Non-Jewish. Yes.
I've lost like the main
is not your legal
child and therefore
therefore well first of all wouldn't be Jewish, but besides the Jewish
aspect, here if let's say if you die they would not inherit
from
you, if you're if you have the child if if you have
a sibling that was the result of your that was your half
sister your half brother because and the mother was a non-Jewish woman
then that sibling wouldn't be involved in the process of ייבום, yibbum,
right? So if a man had a child from a non-Jewish woman
and he died his wife would still be obligated in ייבום, yibbum,
his Jewish wife would still be obligated in ייבום. yibbum. So for
all those הלכות halachos it's not considered a person's legal child.
If it was a sister then it would you're saying?
Yes, absolutely. A ממזר, mamzer, a person had a child with his
sister or with a married woman, even though the child is a
ממזר, mamzer, and then he dies, his wife is exempt from ייבום.
yibbum. And a person also is מקיים פרו ורבו mekayem pru u'revu
by the way. So it's quite ironic, right? That to accept the
idea that there's a difference between ממזר mamzer and legal child. And
two things, first of all right in in our context when we
use the word bastard we mean basically all we mean is the
idea of a legal child, we don't have a different idea of
ממזר, mamzer, and we assume it applies to any child born out
of wedlock. Again by הלכה halacha it's different. ממזר mamzer is any
child born as a result of an איסור כרת, issur kares, and
the only הלכה halacha of a ממזר mamzer I mean it's not
only but it's whatever I mean it's profound but it's really the
only הלכה halacha is that he or she cannot marry a somebody
else a non-ממזר. non-mamzer. Okay but that's not that the person isn't
the person's legal child. So again even if ממזר mamzer results from
a incest or from adultery and all those things, person fulfills פרו
ורבו, pru u'revu, the child inherits him, if the guy dies his
wife is exempt
from ייבום, yibbum, he could be a בכור, bechor, if the guy
dies his wife is exempt from ייבום, yibbum, if he has a
sibling he would do he would have a מצוה mitzvah at he
would have the מצוה mitzvah of ייבום yibbum between him and his
brother would be relevant, all of those things. It's a הלכה halacha
that he can't marry. Okay, I know it's hard to imagine, but
sort of think about it like it's like the category of פצוע
דכא, p'tzu'a daka, okay? We tend to think ממזר mamzer is more
big in terms of your whole legal child, but it's not. It's
just a הלכה halacha of not marrying. So what we're saying is
the only offspring that is not a legal child is one that
results from a non-Jewish mother essentially, either non-Jewish or a slave. Okay,
that is the only type of a child that's not non-Jewish offspring.
Right, although slave is like a quasi-like that, so yes, yes.
A ממזר mamzer can marry a convert.
Right,
that is correct too.
Okay, let's see if the non-Jewish woman converts,
will she and her children be...
they aren't going to be subject to the secondary עריות. arayos.
Okay,
let's not go there. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
What was the question has to do about ייבום yibum and חליצה?
chalitza?
Yeah, ייבום yibum or חליצה. chalitza. I mean, they're not allowed to
do ייבום, yibum, but if he did it, it would be binding
and he has to do חליצה. chalitza. Yeah, exactly. All right, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so בת אשת אביך הוצא
Bas eishess avicha hotzei ואמר רחמנא Ve'amar rachmana אחותך היא achosecha hi
לרבות lerabbos אחותו משפחה achoso mishifcha ואמר רחמנא... ve'amar rachmana... Okay, בת
אשת אביך הוצא Bas eishess avicha hotzei ואמר רחמנא Ve'amar rachmana אחותך
היא. achosecha hi. ואימא... Ve'eima... תיתי? teitei? ואימא Ve'eima בת אשת אביך
כקיים בת אשת אביך הוצא bas eishess avicha kikayam bas eishess avicha
hotzei ואמר רחמנא ve'amar rachmana אחותך היא achosecha hi לרבות lerabbos אחותו
משפחה ועבודת
כוכבים.
achoso mishifcha
ve'avodas kochavim.
So how do
you know that verse that recognizes this offspring as your sister is
when the woman who couldn't be in the house is an איסור
עריות? issur arayos? Maybe it's when the woman who couldn't be in
the house, as it were, the woman who couldn't be married to
your father was a שפחה shifcha or non-Jewish woman? And maybe that's
considered your sibling? Okay, so we have now two categories of people
that marriage is not binding with. One is איסור עריות, issur arayos,
and the other is slave or non-Jewish woman. How do you know
which one to say is a legal offspring and which one is
not? So אמר קרא amar kra בת אשת אביך bas eishess avicha
משיש לו אישות לאביך בה, misheyesh lo ishuss le'avicha bah, a woman
that marriage is possible, פרט לאחותו משפחה ומעבודת כוכבים. perat le'achoso mishifcha
u'me'avodas kochavim. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ומה ראית? u'mah ra'isa?
Again, fine, you have two categories now, marriage isn't possible either with
עריות arayos or with non-Jewish woman. What allows you to say that
one is a legal offspring and one is not? מסתברא, Mistabra, חייבי
כריתות הוה ליה לרבות. chayavei krisos hava lei lerabbos.
Now, it makes sense that the incest prohibitions, the עריות arayos prohibitions,
it is a legal child. Why? שכן תופסין בה קידושין לאחריני. sheken
tofsin bah kiddushin le'achreini.
Because somebody else could marry them. Might be your sister, but somebody
else could marry her. So קידושין kiddushin is not completely out of
the category. As opposed to a non-Jewish woman or a slave woman,
no Jew could marry her. So that's completely excluded from the category.
אדרבה, Adarabah, the opposite says the גמרא. Gemara. שפחה ועבודת כוכבים הוה
ליה לרבות. shifcha ve'avodas kochavim hava lei lerabbos. You should have included
the children of a non-Jewish woman and a slave. דאי מגיירא de'ei
migayra לדידיה נמי תפסי בה קידושין. ledidei nami tafsi bah kiddushin.
Because they are at least theoretically able to be... you're theoretically able
to marry them. All they have to do is convert or be
freed. As opposed to your sister, you could never marry. So maybe
from your perspective, these women are considered more potentially
marriageable, and therefore should more be considered your child? So the גמרא
Gemara says לכי מגיירא, lichi migayra, fine. When she'll convert, we'll talk
about it. But right now, in her current status, she is completely
off-limits to you and to all Jews, as opposed to your sister
that is not right now completely out of the category of marriage.
So therefore, yes, ironically we include עריות, arayos, even though marriage is
impossible between you and this woman, because it is possible between her
and other Jews. And therefore she is fundamentally within the marriageable context
and therefore the child is your legal child as opposed to a
non-Jewish woman, the child of a non-Jewish woman or of a slave.
In other words... I'm sorry, I skipped a line. לכי מגיירא גופא
אחרינא היא. lichi migayra gufa achrina hi. I'm sorry. Okay. When she
converts,
she's another person. Then she'll be like כקטן שנולד. kekatan shenolad. But
right now, I'm sorry, I stopped too short. So therefore right now,
in this state, she is not marriageable at all by you. You
can't say hypothetically she's
marriageable by me because then she would be considered legally a different
person. So as this person, right, and that's what we said before
about the whole כקטן שנולד. kekatan shenolad. So this person is not
marriageable by you now and not even theoretically marriageable by you because
were she to convert she would be actually legally considered a different
person. Yeah.
So the two categories are forbidden marriage as opposed to
something else.
Well, there's three categories. There's well four categories. There's extra-marital, which has
not even
a הוה אמינא hava amina that clearly not a problem. Negative prohibition,
marriage is not allowed but marriage is still binding. Also there, more
obvious that the offspring in that case, even in or out of
marriage, since in theory marriage is possible, is a legal child. And
then we have the two final ones, which is prohibited by כרת,
kares, where marriage is not only not allowed but not binding, and
a non-Jewish woman or a slave. And both of those, marriage is
impossible. theoretically possible, one of them the child is your legal child
with the איסור עריות, issur arayos, even though the child was a
ממזר, mamzer, the other is not. And the גמרא Gemara says the
basic difference is that in the כרת kares case this woman is
still marriageable within the Jewish community and since she's not completely excluded
from the category as opposed to the non-Jewish woman who no Jew
could marry her, she's completely excluded and even though hypothetically she could
convert, that would make her legally a different person. Yes Avery?
If a woman converts after she's already had the child, what's the
status of the child to the man? Is that his child?
No. קטן שנולד, katan shenolad, no legal relationship. No legal? Right. Yeah
you had a question Phil?
No? Okay. Give me a very technical question, but I'm asking it
anyway. So let's hypothetical, so you sleep with you know a married
woman, right? Yeah. Adultery, don't you both have to be put to
death? So how come this, so then isn't the
child, how can the child be considered yours in any way to
inherit you?
It's like a bastard inheriting you. What do you mean? No what
do you mean? There weren't witnesses. There weren't witnesses.
I don't know.
Okay. Alright moving on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay.
ורבנן, ve-rabbanan, so the rabbis all that was learned from the פסוק
posuk of your sister, the daughter of your father's wife, that's only
your legal sister if your father could have theoretically married the mother.
ורבנן, ve-rabbanan, the rabbis who learn that to tell you there's a
separate prohibition of
when it's also your father's wife's daughter, so and they learn it
out for a law about עריות, arayos, where do they know this
idea of what's considered a legal sibling or a legal child? למעוטי
שפחה ועבודת כוכבים מנלן? le-ma'utei shifcha ve-avodat kochavim menalan? Where do they
know the idea to exclude a child of a slave or of
a non-Jewish woman that that's not your legal child? נפקא להו מהאשה
וילדיה תהיה לאדוניה. nafka lehu me-ha-ishah ve-yeladeha tihyeh la-adoneha. It says by
the case about a woman, a slave who's had children, that they
should be for the master, not for the father. So you see
they're not considered the offspring of the father. Now that's of course
the maid, the slave,
that's not the case of the non-Jewish woman, we'll get to that.
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rebbe Yosi be-Rebbe Yehuda, what would רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה Rebbe Yosi be-Rebbe Yehuda say, who doesn't get it from
that פסוק? posuk? Why? That's a pretty obvious פסוק, posuk, so why
does he need two פסוקים? psukim? חד בשפחה וחד בעבודת כוכבים. chad
be-shifcha ve-chad be-avodat kochavim. One פסוק posuk is by the slave and
one is by a non-Jewish woman. וצריכי, ve-tzrichi, you need both. דאי
אשמעינן שפחה, de-ee ashmeinan shifcha, had it just said the offspring of
a slave is not your child, משום דלית להו חייס, mishum de-leit
lehu chayis, because they're not considered to have general family recognized, you
know,
relationships. I mean this is a, you know, to some degree it
reflects the sort of societal reality, you know, that slave families were
often broken up and so on and slaves would often be, you
know, sort of sexual property and questions about knowing who's related to
whom and so on. But הלכתית halachically what that means is is
that even as slaves they're not really recognized in terms of their
familial relationships. And therefore it's more obvious that the offspring of a
slave would not be recognized to be the child of the husband
or of the father. אבל עבודת כוכבים דאית לה חייס, aval avodat
kochavim de-it lah chayis, but non-Jews that are considered to be related,
you know, child to parent, and the familial relationships generally are legally
recognized, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe that would not be excluded and
maybe the offspring with a non-Jewish woman would be a legal child.
So you need to tell me even a non-Jewish woman. ואי אשמעינן
עבודת כוכבים, ve-ee ashmeinan avodat kochavim, had it just said in the
case of a non-Jewish woman, משום דלא שייכא במצות, mishum de-lo shaycha
be-mitzvot, that's cause she's out of the Jewish category completely and therefore
the offspring wouldn't be recognized. אבל שפחה דשייכא במצות, aval shifcha de-shaycha
be-mitzvot, a Jewish female slave, right? All slaves, it's the case of
עבד כנעני, eved kena'ani, are obligated in the negative prohibitions and in
the positive non-time-bound like women. So they actually have a very full
type of מצוה mitzvah obligation. And therefore quasi-Jewish, right? Maybe the reason
the offspring with a non-Jewish woman is not just because קידושין kiddushin
isn't binding, maybe it's because she's completely not Jewish. Maybe a slave
that's like quasi-Jewish, maybe the child would be your child. דאימא לא,
צריכא. de-eima lo, tzricha. So you need to say both cases and
that nicely points out the different type of logic behind them. Like
the non-Jewish woman, that's what we talk about matrilineal descent: mother isn't
Jewish, child isn't Jewish, if child isn't Jewish, not considered your child.
Okay, whereas by the slave it's less about the Jewish identity and
more about the fact that that's not like recognized at all in
the concept of a type of a familial relationship. All right, וכי
תימא, ve-ki teima, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. ורבנן, ve-rabbanan,
so that's why you need two פסוקים. psukim. So how about the
rabbis? אשכחן שפחה, ashkan shifcha, fine, you have the פסוק posuk of
האשה וילדיה ha-ishah ve-yeladeha to tell me about a slave. עבודת כוכבים
מנלן? avodat kochavim menalan? Where do you know non-Jewish mother, the child
is not considered your legal child? This is really the question about
matrilineal descent. How do you know when it's the mother is not
Jewish the child is not yours but also means not Jewish? Okay
here, so how do you know that? וכי תימא נילף משפחה? ve-ki
teima neelef mi-shifcha? Well, we learn it out from the case of
the slave woman. No, הנך מצטרכי, hanach mitztrachi, like we said, you
need a special פסוק posuk for each one. Slave on the one
hand is because there is no familial relationships. That doesn't necessarily exclude
non-Jewish mother where there are familial relationships. So how do you know
to exclude non-Jewish mother? אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so here
it is, the big פסוק pasuk that's the basis for the idea,
at least in the גמרא, Gemara, the quoted basis for the idea
that a non-Jewish mother the child isn't Jewish. משום רבי שמעון בן
יוחי, Mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai, אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse
says, כי יסיר את בנך מאחרי. Ki yasir et bincha me-acharai. This
is a case about not marrying off your, not taking non-Jewish children,
so not taking, marrying amongst non-Jews. So the פסוק pasuk is, I
forget how the
פסוק pasuk goes, לא תתחתן בם, Lo titchaten bam, לא תתחתן בם,
Lo titchaten bam, בתך—what Bitcha is it?—לא תקח לבנו, Lo tikach livno,
לא תקח לבנו? Lo tikach livno? Don't take their daughter for your
son. ובתו לא תקח לבנך, U-vito lo tikach le-vincha, right, because the
daughters are always the ones changing their domicile. ובתו לא
תקח
לבנך.
U-vito lo
tikach le-vincha. Why? כי יסיר
את בנך מאחרי.
Ki yasir
et bincha me-acharai. Now there's a problem with this פסוק. pasuk. He
will lead your son away from me presumably is going on don't
take a daughter for your son because it'll lead your son away
from me, but then it should be כי תסיר את בנך. Ki
tasir et bincha. She will, the non-Jewish woman will take your son,
take your daughter away from your son. So it doesn't make sense.
What's the כי יסיר? ki yasir? So based on the כי יסיר
ki yasir the דרשה drasha is that we're going back to בתך
לא תקח לבנו. bitcha lo tikach livno. Don't let then don't let
their men marry your daughters. Why? Because your daughter will marry out
and the husbands, so your daughter's husband, the non-Jewish husbands
will take your son, meaning your grandson, away from me. That's how
it's read because of the יסיר, yasir, so the only person who's
the male here who could lead your son away would be the
non-Jewish husband. So how are they taking your sons away from me?
They're taking your grandsons away from me, which means the offspring of
a non-Jewish husband and a Jewish woman is still your grandson, is
still your child. That's how we learn and then we say that
we'll say the same in reverse. Let's read this. אמר קרא כי
יסיר את בנך מאחרי. Amar kra ki yasir et bincha me-acharai. So
בנך מישראלית איקרי בנך, Bincha mi-Yisraelit itkarei bincha, your son, meaning your
grandson that from the Jewish woman from your daughter is still your
grandson and therefore the husbands will take your grandsons away from me.
ואין בנך הבא מן העובדת כוכבים, Ve-ein bincha haba min ha-ovedet kochavim,
but in the reverse case where your sons took non-Jewish women, דלא
איקרי בנך, de-la itkarei bincha, that's not your son, אלא בנה, ela
bna, that's her son, and she's not Jewish. So there we get
the idea of matrilineal descent, all from that little יוד. yud.
So
therefore we know that if it's not your son, A, not Jewish
and B, also not legally your son for all these other areas
for inheritance and all these other things. I guess in theory you
could have imagined that it's not Jewish but still he inherits from
me. The idea here, I'm throwing in the not Jewish. The גמרא's
Gemara concern is more directly about is it legally considered part of
your family or not. Who are his siblings, who's his father? But
obviously connected to this idea of not being your son is also
the other idea of not being Jewish. But let's just finish the
little bit. I'll take the question. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, שמע מינה,
shma mina, we hear from this, בן בתך הבא מן עובד כוכבים
איקרי
בנך. ben bitcha haba min oved kochavim itkarei bincha.
That, which is pretty much what we just said, your grandson that
comes from a non-Jewish father but a Jewish mother is still your
son. Fine. לימא קסבר רבינא, Leima kasavar Ravina, עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא
על בת ישראל הולד כשר? oved kochavim ve-eved haba al bat Yisrael
havlad kasher? So one minute, so can we therefore infer from this
that now that we're saying that it's still your son with a
Jewish mother and a non-Jewish father, still your grandson, and we're seeming
to say it's not problematic at all. So should we say the
child is completely כשר, kasher, meaning not a ממזר? mamzer? You might
remember before we had the idea that a non-Jewish father makes the
child a ממזר. mamzer. We don't rule that way, thankfully. But the
גמרא Gemara is saying so that sounds like what you're saying here,
you're saying it's your son, not problematic. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, we're not saying totally not problematic. נהי דממזר לא הוי, Nehi
de-mamzer lo havei, it wouldn't be a ממזר, mamzer, בכשרות נמי לא
הוי. be-chashrut nami lo havei. We wouldn't say that the child is
totally כשר. kasher. ישראל פסול מקרי. Yisrael pasul mikrei. It would still
be considered somehow an invalid ישראל. Yisrael. So he's your son, legally
your son, he's not a ממזר, mamzer, he's Jewish, but there's still
some type of a problematic that he had a non-Jewish father. Now
the גמרא Gemara here doesn't elaborate on this, but this becomes a
large discussion elsewhere, and a big discussion להלכה le-halacha because normally you
say what's the legal status, halakhic status of somebody who had a
Jewish mother, not Jewish father? You say fine, whatever, Jewish, no problem,
obviously they wouldn't be a כהן kohen or a לוי levi if
it was a boy. But actually, this גמרא Gemara indicates that the
fact of a non-Jewish father, you might remember we even had a
position before that he would be a ממזר. mamzer. The גמרא Gemara
is rejecting it, but the fact of a non-Jewish father might create
some idea of a פסול, psul, and that becomes an issue, a
debate whether we פוסק pasken that way, and the big issue is
about whether if it's a woman, whether she can marry a כהן.
Kohen. A woman who has had a Jewish mother and a non-Jewish
father, is there some idea of a פסול psul that enough creates
a problem for a כהן? Kohen? That is a major debate in
the גמרא, Gemara, in the ראשונים, Rishonim, and so on, big, big
issue, that's hinted to over here. I'll take... I see those hands,
I just want to read to get to the bottom and then
we'll take the questions. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: הא בשבע
אומות כתיב? ha beshiva umot ketiv? One minute. This פסוק pasuk here,
it says: לא תתחתן בם, lo titchaten bam, don't intermarry with them.
It's talking about when you go into the land and the seven
Canaanite nations. So maybe all of this is only by the seven
Canaanite nations. That was my question. Okay, good. So you see, you
wait long enough, all the questions are answered. It's only by the
seven Canaanite nations and by others maybe it is considered your son.
Okay, because remember, now we're saying that this is a פסוק pasuk
that is the basis of saying that the offspring with a non-Jewish
woman is not your son. Maybe that's only for the Canaanite nations
it's true. So the גמרא Gemara says: כי יסיר לרבות כל המסירים.
ki yasir l'rabot kol hamessirim. No, it says: when they lead away,
they will lead away your son from me. That idea, that the
possibility of intermarriage causes your, you know, your children to be led
astray, that concept is relevant to all non-Jewish intermarriage and therefore it's
not limited to the שבעה עממים. shiva amamim. So the גמרא Gemara
says: one minute, הניחא לרבי שמעון דדרש טעמא דקרא? ha nicha l'Rabbi
Shimon d'darash ta'ama de-kra? That's good according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that's willing to say the, you know, that we look at the
reason behind the פסוק pasuk and therefore we understand... we interpret its
parameters based on the reason. So a good example of this or
the classic example is it says, you know, you're not allowed to
take collateral the garment of a אלמנה. almanah. So what if it's
a rich widow? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says: oh, well, in that
case it's okay. And רבנן Rabbanan say: no, you know, it says
widow, it doesn't mean... categorically. But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon thinks that
we can identify the reason behind the פסוק. pasuk. I won't go
into now what that reason is, but like, I think we can
all understand intuitively that when the תורה Torah speaks about widows, presumably
we think it's talking about poor widows. Okay, so he says we
can identify the reason and use the reason we understand to interpret
the parameters of the prohibition or of the מצוה. mitzvah. So that's
דרשינן טעמא דקרא. darshinan ta'ama de-kra. So it says according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, if it's... I'm explaining this just right now a
little different than רש"י Rashi for simplicity's sake, some other time we'll
worry about רש"י, Rashi, but he says, it says כי יסיר בנך,
ki yasir bincha, it's telling you what the concern is. So if
the concern is כי יסיר בנך, ki yasir bincha, that'll tell you
that we're talking about כל המסירים, kol hamessirim, anybody that can lead
your son astray, not just the שבע אומות. sheva umot. So according
to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, this פסוק pasuk is talking about all
non-Jews and that's where we learn that the children of non-Jewish women
are not your children. So the גמרא Gemara says: okay, so that's
good for רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אלא לרבנן מנא להו? ela l'Rabbanan
mena lehu? The רבנן Rabbanan who don't agree with רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, where do they know that the offspring of a non-Jewish woman
is not your child? Maybe this is only by the שבע אומות.
sheva umot. So the גמרא Gemara says: מאן תנא דפליג עליה דרבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה, רבי שמעון היא? man tanna d'palig alei d'Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda, Rabbi Shimon hi? No, remember we said up until now
that רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda knows the offspring
of a non-Jewish woman is not your child from the פסוק pasuk
about ערוות בת אשת אביך, ervat bat eshet avicha, only a child
that your father could have had, could have married the mother. So
this question, that we need a different פסוק, pasuk, is only for
those that argue with רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda.
Right, is that clear? Remember רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda learned the idea that it's only a child of a... of
an offspring that marriage could have been possible from the פסוק pasuk
of ערוות בת אשת אביך. ervat bat eshet avicha. Then we've been
saying, oh, but those that argue with him, where do they learn
this idea of the child of a non-Jewish woman? So now we're
saying that you learn it from כי יסיר בנך. ki yasir bincha.
This only works according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Fine, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon will be the opinion that argues on רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda. So if you don't hold of
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
and you don't hold that you can learn out the Canaanite nations
here... all the nations here, you'll learn out this idea from the
פסוק pasuk that רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda has
about the daughter of your father's wife. You had a question here.
I'm going back to the case where the Jewish man and the
non-Jewish woman have a child. Yeah. Then if the woman converts, she
becomes then his wife, right? No, you asked that before. No, the
answer is no. I was asking it a different way. I didn't
ask if she converted the child. No, no, no. And even if
she converts, they would still have to get married in order to
become, you know, to be married. Right. Oh, I see. So the
child forever... everybody... right. Exactly. Exactly. Yeah. Why does the גמרא Gemara
have to make a distinction between שפחה shifcha and עובדת כוכבים? ovedet
kochavim? They're both non-Jewish. No, because a שפחה shifcha is quasi-Jewish and
she's חייבת במצוות. chayevet be-mitzvot. Just because she's on the... process... yeah,
she's close to becoming Jewish. Yeah, I mean she's not just close,
she's in some middle state and she's obligated in מצוות. mitzvot. Yeah.
Does the that language of צור tzur for for the the Jewish
woman and the non-Jewish man just simply mean from being a כהן
Kohen or לוי? Levi? Like cause they don't... No, so the גמרא
Gemara gives an explicit on what פסול pasul means. I'm not, we're
not just saying it's based on this word. There's other גמרות Gemarot
that are part of this conversation. Like from this גמרא Gemara you
would not have known what the word פסול pasul means. Right, exactly.
All right, so that was a pretty heavy גמרא Gemara about the
idea about legal children, it's a again that the ממזר mamzer people
can be a anyone with ממזר mamzer is still a legal offspring
and a legal sibling, just means can't marry another you know naturally
born Jew, and that a child born out of wedlock certainly isn't
a legally you know does not have a different legal status, and
the only issue would be a child born from a slave or
a non-Jewish woman which we learn is person's not a person's legal
child and also we know not considered Jewish, but here the emphasis
was not legal child. Yes. Is the גמרא Gemara in this סוגיא
sugia assuming that עובדת כוכבים ovedet kochavim is not שייך shayach to
שבע מצוות בני נח? sheva mitzvot bnei Noach? That's not relevant. It's
not שייך shayach to our world of מצוה. mitzva. Okay, משנה mishna
next now משנה mishna כג עמוד ב. chaf gimmel amud bet. Back
to יבמות. Yevamot. I wonder how many people are
saying, oh good, we get back to יבמות Yevamot topic? Well, we're
back to יבמות Yevamot topic. Okay, so we're done with the עריות
arayot and we're done with the ממזר mamzer issue. What's that? That's
my... I have a weird ringtone. I gotta change it. Okay, anyway.
Oh my god. All right, משנה. mishna. מי שקידש אחת משתי אחיות
ואין ידוע איזו מהם קידש mi she-kidesh achat
mishtei achayot ve-ein yodea eizo mehem kidesh נותן גט לזו וגט לזו.
noten get lazo ve-get lazo. So ראובן Reuven went over to רחל
Rachel and לאה Leah and he gave them קידוש kiddush and he
married one of them and let's make it better. יעקב Yaakov went
over to רחל Rachel and לאה Leah and he married one of
them and he didn't know which one he married. Okay. So how
exactly you don't know which one you married? You forgot? You made
some תנאי? tnai? Anyway, identical twins? Father-in-law mixes them up? Okay, anyway.
So they were under a veil when he gave them money. נותן
גט לזו וגט לזו. noten get lazo ve-get lazo. So he can't
continue he can't marry either one of them, right, because if he
goes ahead and marries one, it might be his wife's sister. So
he can't live with either one of them even after divorce. So
he has to divorce both. And they want to go ahead now.
He can't live with them. They want to marry other men. So
he has to allow them to marry other men. So he has
to give a גט get to each one of them. Each one
might be his wife. Okay. Now מת, met, now if he dies
ולא אח אחד velo ach echad and he has one brother, חולץ
לשתיהם. choletz lishteihem. This person would have to do חליצה chalitza to
both of them. Why? Because he can't do רחל Rachel and לאה
Leah now fall before... We'll make it... We'll stop being cute. So
ראובן Reuven went ahead and he marries either רחל Rachel or לאה.
Leah. Doesn't know who. ראובן Reuven dies. Now שמעון. Shimon. So if
שמעון Shimon goes ahead and does יבום yibum with רחל, Rachel, רחל
Rachel that might be okay, but it might be לאה Leah is
really his sister-in-law and then he just had sex with אחות זקוקתו.
achot zekukato. Remember אחות זקוקתו? achot zekukato? Right. לאה Leah would be
quasi-married. Same would be if he would go ahead and do יבום
yibum with לאה. Leah. If she's really his sister-in-law, fine, but it
might be not his sister-in-law, רחל's Rachel sister-in-law, then he just had
sex with אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. So he goes ahead and he
does חליצה. chalitza. Okay. Now, if he did חליצה chalitza to רחל,
Rachel, okay, if רחל Rachel was actually his sister-in-law, good, לאה Leah
could walk off, end of day, and he could even choose now...
He could not go ahead though and marry לאה. Leah. Why not?
Because then that would be אחות achot not זקוקתו zekukato anymore, but
אחות חלוצתו. achot chalutzato. Okay. We haven't discussed this yet, but if
you did חליצה, chalitza, that becomes quasi-like divorce. And if a man
divorced a woman, right, he cannot marry a woman and her sister
בחייה. bechayeha. His first wife would have to die. Just because he's
divorced from his first wife, he still cannot marry the sister. Right?
Is that clear? Can't marry two sisters, two siblings, as long as
one of them is still alive. So if he did חליצה chalitza
with רחל, Rachel, then רחל Rachel is חלוצתו chalutzato and he cannot
go ahead and marry לאה Leah because that would be אחות זקוקתו.
achot zekukato. Okay. If רחל Rachel actually wasn't his sister-in-law, then it'd
be fine. Then the חליצה chalitza is meaningless and he could go
ahead and do יבום yibum or you know or חליצה chalitza with
לאה. Leah. But because רחל Rachel might have been his sister-in-law and
he had to do חליצה chalitza with her, he can't go ahead
at this stage and marry לאה. Leah. Okay, so therefore he has
to do חליצה chalitza with both. Each one of them needs to
be freed. There's no way he can do יבום yibum with one.
There's no way he can do חליצה chalitza with one and יבום
yibum with the other. He has to do חליצה chalitza with both.
Right. Is that pretty clear? Did I illustrate that? You got it?
Okay, fine. Okay, now. Okay, fine. Okay, now היו לו שנים. hayu
lo shnayim. Now let's say he had two brothers שמעון Shimon and
לוי. Levi. אחד חולץ ואחד מיבם. echad choleitz v'echad meyabem. Now this
case, this let's also illustrate. Okay. So you've got ראובן Reuven there
who's who you have here רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah. Okay, we
don't know which one he's married to, then he dies. Okay, now
you've got שמעון Shimon and לוי. Levi. Now, one of them does
חליצה Chalitzah and one does יבום. Yibum. Why? Okay, let's say שמעון
Shimon does חליצה Chalitzah with רחל. Rachel. Okay, he does חליצה. Chalitzah.
So now, if רחל Rachel is actually his sister-in-law, fine. So then
he did חליצה Chalitzah with her, and that was all she needed,
and לוי Levi can go ahead and marry לאה, Leah, do יבום
Yibum with לאה. Leah. Why? Because לאה Leah anyway was not even
married at all. It's not, she's not אחות חלוצתו, achos chalutzaso, he
isn't the one that did חליצה, Chalitzah, right? It's only because he
did חליצה Chalitzah it becomes like they were quasi-married, like it was
a quasi-divorce. So then this is completely irrelevant. This was the יבום
Yibum story, and he's free to go ahead and, why not, marry
לאה? Leah? That would be if רחל Rachel actually was the wife.
Let's say it turned out, what was his sister-in-law, let's say רחל
Rachel wasn't his sister-in-law, let's say לאה Leah was the sister-in-law. Okay,
so this act of חליצה Chalitzah was meaningless, okay, it was done
to some random woman, okay, and then he's doing יבום Yibum with
לאה. Leah. Wonderful. So that also works. So one does חליצה Chalitzah
with one, the other does יבום Yibum with the other. Now, you
cannot, you have to do it in that order. Because if he
starts by doing יבום Yibum with לאה, Leah, that works if לאה
Leah is the sister-in-law. But if לאה Leah isn't his sister-in-law and
רחל Rachel is his sister-in-law, then he just had sex with אחות
זיקוקתו, achos zikukaso, right? So first you have to remove his relationship
with רחל, Rachel, do חליצה Chalitzah in case she is the sister-in-law,
that gets stopped here, she's no longer זיקוקתו, zikukaso, she's now חלוצתו
chalutzaso because שמעון Shimon did the חליצה, Chalitzah, and that frees him
up to do יבום Yibum with לאה. Leah. Yes.
So, but if רחל Rachel is the wife, yeah, and then לאה
Leah isn't anything to ראובן, Reuven, right?
And then
שמעון Shimon does חליצה Chalitzah with רחל, Rachel, right? And then לוי
Levi marries לאה, Leah, why would you call it יבום? Yibum? Call
it, it's just No, no, you're right.
If this is the יבום Yibum scenario then that's marriage, correct.
But then what if he doesn't know if he needs to do
יבום Yibum or marriage, isn't that a
No, because יבום Yibum is always preceded with מאמר, ma'amar, with some
קידושין kiddushin anyway, a normal יבום Yibum done the right way.
מאמר Ma'amar and קידושין? kiddushin?
Yeah, yeah, you would do a קידושין kiddushin and יבום Yibum too.
Right, you wouldn't just do יבום. Yibum. Why?
Should you do מאמר ma'amar just in case? Would you do that?
No, you always do מאמר ma'amar preceding יבום Yibum if you're doing
it the right way. So it's a good question.
If it's not יבום, Yibum, then do you do מאמר? ma'amar?
Yes, if it's not יבום, Yibum, מאמר ma'amar is קידושין. kiddushin. Any
יבום Yibum is preceded by an act of קידושין, kiddushin, rabbinically. So
even if this is so it's a good question, even if this
is
not his sister-in-law, part of the practice of יבום Yibum consists of
מאמר, ma'amar, which is קידושין, kiddushin, and יבום, Yibum, which is basically
like נישואין nissuin and they have sex. Yeah, in his act of
יבום Yibum he's doing an act of קידושין kiddushin and נישואין. nissuin.
What?
Totally just semantics, they're basically the same act.
Well, this is semantics to let you know that this is and
this is rabbinic because, you know, it's to let you know that
this is in the context of יבום Yibum and this is rabbinic.
Okay, but the act is the same act. This isn't exactly the
same act, this is sex, this is like חופה chuppah etc, which
is the context of sex but not exactly the act of sex
per se. Okay, but it boils down to pretty much the same
thing.
All right, so now, קידשו וכנסו אין מוציאין מידם. kidshu v'khinsu ein
motzin mi-yadam. Let's say they went ahead and שמעון Shimon did
not do
חליצה. Chalitzah. שמעון Shimon went ahead and did and did יבום Yibum
with רחל Rachel or what looked like יבום Yibum and he did
יבום Yibum with לאה. Leah. So in that case, okay, when שמעון
Shimon did יבום Yibum with רחל Rachel he did a bad thing,
because because רחל Rachel might not have been his sister-in-law and then
he was having sex with אחות זיקוקתו, achos zikukaso, okay, he shouldn't
have done that. That was bad, he shouldn't have had sex with
אחות זיקוקתו. achos zikukaso. But he went ahead and did it. Now
לוי Levi went ahead and did יבום Yibum with לאה. Leah. Okay,
now in this case, that was totally fine, because that was the
one he had זיקה zika with and that was an act of
יבום. Yibum. Now שמעון Shimon בדיעבד bedi'avad can continue living with רחל
Rachel because she stops being אחות זיקוקתו achos zikukaso because as soon
as לוי Levi did יבום Yibum with לאה, Leah, any relationship לאה
Leah had to שמעון Shimon went away, right? She was only זיקוקתו
zikukaso because it had to be sort of, you know, it was
supposed to have been because there was a מצוה mitzvah of יבום.
Yibum. Is this clear? I get some blank stares here, right? Okay,
if לאה Leah wound up being the real sister-in-law, then we had
a problem. שמעון Shimon was not allowed to have sex with רחל
Rachel because it was אחות זיקוקתו. achos zikukaso. But this is זיקוקתה
zikukasa only because there was a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum that
was waiting to be done. Once לוי Levi went ahead and did
the מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum with לאה Leah afterwards, then this
לאה Leah stops having any relationship with שמעון. Shimon. She's no longer
זיקוקתה, zikukaso, she's not חלוצתו, chalutzaso, and שמעון Shimon can continue living
with רחל. Rachel. Okay? Yes, clear? So that's why if they בדיעבד
bedieved did it, although שמעון Shimon the first one who did the
act of sex was wrong because that might have been אחות זיקוקתה,
achos zikukaso, they're allowed to continue to stay married after they've both
done יבום. yibum. Okay. Where were we? בקיצור המציא מידו בשנים שקדשו
שתי אחיות. bekitzur hamtzi miyado bishnayim shekidshu shtei achayos. Now let's say
you have זה אינו יודע איזה קידש וזה אינו יודע איזה קידש.
zeh eino yodeia eizeh kidesh
vezeh eino yodeia eizeh kidesh. Okay? זה נותן שני גיטין וזה נותן
שני גיטין. zeh nosein shnei gittin vezeh nosein shnei gittin. Now let's
first make it more confusing. So ראובן Reuven did a קידוש kiddush
and שמעון Shimon both maybe did some type of a weird thing
so we don't know who's and they both did it with both
sisters. Okay? So each one of these sisters well one is only
married each one only did it with one with one of them
but anyway one might one is married to one, one is married
to the other. We don't know I guess one to be I
guess one could be married to none of them if one did
the same act with the one that was already married but anyway,
okay it's the same type of scenario except except it's worse because
he married to two sisters. Yeah right except except except we don't
know except it's not just
we don't know who's married to
ראובן, Reuven, we also don't know
which one of them is
married to שמעון. Shimon. Okay. So שני אחים shnei achim בשנים שקדשו
שתי אחיות. bishnayim shekidshu shtei achayos. זה אינו יודע איזה קידש וזה
אינו יודע איזה קידש. zeh eino yodeia eizeh kidesh vezeh eino yodeia
eizeh kidesh. זה נותן שני גיטין וזה נותן שני גיטין. zeh nosein
shnei gittin vezeh nosein shnei gittin. So you want to free them
obviously you can't consummate the marriage because it might be your wife's
sister. True about ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. You want to free
them you have to give a גט get to each one of
them. Each one has to give a גט get to both because
you know any one רחל Rachel might need a גט get from
ראובן Reuven or she might need it from שמעון. Shimon. לאה Leah
might need it from ראובן, Reuven, לאה Leah might need it from
so they need two גיטין gittin from each one of them.
מתו, meisu, now they both died.
לזה אח ולזה אח.
lezeh
ach ulezeh ach.
Okay each one has a brother. Actually I shouldn't have done ראובן
Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, I should have done an unrelated person. ראובן
Reuven and who? Let's say גרשום Gershom here. גרשום, Gershom, I'm going
to do ברק. Barak. I like him ברק. Barak. Okay. They die.
Okay. Now you got שמעון Shimon here and ברק Barak I don't
know who you have. You'll have נמרוד. Nimrod. We'll have some biblical
names. Okay, so anyway, alright. So okay, מתו. meisu. לזה אח ולזה
אח. lezeh ach ulezeh ach. זה חולץ לשניהם וזה חולץ לשניהם.
zeh choletz leshneihem
vezeh choletz leshneihem.
Each brother the same way the live brother had to do had
to do a גט get is the same as the live you
know the same way the husband had to do a גט, get,
the surviving brother does חליצה, chalitzah, same idea. Okay. זה חולץ זה
חולץ. zeh choletz zeh choletz. לזה אחד ולזה שנים. lezeh echad ulezeh
shnayim. Now he had one brother, he had two brothers. Okay so
what are you going to do? לזה אחד ולזה שנים. lezeh echad
ulezeh shnayim. היחיד חולץ לשניהם. hayachid choletz leshneihem. So נמרוד Nimrod there
gives
a
גט get to does חליצה chalitzah to both the same
way his his his brother the original the husband would have given
a גט get to both. והשנים. vehashnayim.
So now basically if he's done a חליצה chalitzah to both of
them he's
this whole relevance of this has basically been pushed aside. We've neutralized
the presence of another possible husband. So then you're back to the
original scenario. ראובן Reuven was married to one, we don't know which
one. What did we say when he was married to one
and we don't know which one?
אחד חולץ ואחד מיבם. echad choletz ve'echad meyabeim. Right? The fact that
we had another one fine, you did your חליצה, chalitzah, you got
out of the picture. And now we're back to a guy who
died with two brothers. So in that case היחיד חולץ לשניהם והשנים
אחד חולץ ואחד מיבם. hayachid choletz leshneihem vehashnayim echad choletz ve'echad meyabeim.
One does חליצה chalitzah one does יבום. yibum. Cause the חליצה chalitzah
either it worked and that was the sister-in-law and then the יבום
yibum is just סתם stam marrying a woman marrying another woman. Or
the חליצה chalitzah was the wrong person but and then he could
do יבום yibum the
real act of יבום yibum and it wouldn't be you know אחות
חלוצתו achos chalutzaso cause
לוי Levi wasn't the one who did חליצה, chalitzah, שמעון Shimon was
the one who did חליצה. chalitzah. Okay. קדמו וכנסו. kidmu vekansu. ובקיצור
uvkitzur if they went ahead and they both did יבום yibum אין
מוציאין מידם. ein motzi'in miyadam. They're allowed to remain married because now
basically even though the first act might have been אחות זיקוקתה, achos
zikukaso, now that the brother is married to the other woman, everything
is okay like we said before. Okay. לזה שנים ולזה שנים. lezeh
shnayim ulezeh shnayim. Each one has two brothers.
We got שמעון Shimon and לוי Levi here and I don't know
נמרוד Nimrod and עשו Esav down here. Okay I don't know why
I'm giving ברק Barak such bad brothers. Alright, anyway.
So clearly they're not part of יעקב's Yaakov family is why. לזה
שנים ולזה שנים. lezeh shnayim ulezeh shnayim. אחיו של זה חולץ לאחת
לאחת ואחיו של זה חולץ לאחת. achiv shel zeh choletz leachas leachas
ve'achiv shel zeh choletz leachas. אחיו של זה מיבם חלוצתו של זה
ואחיו של זה מיבם. achiv shel zeh meyabeim chalutzaso shel zeh ve'achiv
shel zeh meyabeim. מיבם חלוצתו של זה. meyavem chalutzaso shel ze. Okay,
so this is already a little bit more interesting. In this case,
basically here's what we do. שמעון Shimon does חליצה chalitzah with רחל
Rachel and נמרו Nimro does חליצה chalitzah with לאה. Leah. And therefore,
and now לוי Levi does יבום yibum with לאה Leah and עשו
Esav does יבום yibum with רחל. Rachel. Okay, why does that work?
It works in the following way. Okay, שמעון Shimon did חליצה chalitzah
with רחל. Rachel. Okay, so רחל Rachel is now, if there were
no other brothers, we said, שמעון Shimon does חליצה chalitzah with רחל
Rachel and לוי Levi does יבום yibum with לאה. Leah. That's what
we had said before, right? Because that either makes this was the
יבום yibum situation and then he's marrying just סתם stam a woman,
or this was like the unnecessary act and then he's doing יבום.
yibum. Okay, so that's what we said before. The only thing is
that he can't just straight do יבום yibum with לאה Leah because
לאה Leah might have been married to, right, might have been married
to ברק. Barak. Okay, and therefore now that ברק Barak is dead,
she is waiting for יבום. yibum. The woman waiting for יבום yibum
is not allowed סתם stam marry another guy. So that's why she
got חליצה chalitzah from נמרו. Nimro. No problem. So in case she
was the one that was married to ברק, Barak, she's freed because
she got חליצה chalitzah from נמרו. Nimro. So this, this חליצה chalitzah
frees her. This is the scenario we dealt with before, right? That's
the way to look at it. ראובן Reuven dies, one person does
חליצה, chalitzah, one does יבום, yibum, right? The only problem is because
ברק Barak was married to one of them, maybe she can't do
יבום, yibum, maybe she was married to ברק. Barak. Okay, fine, נמרו
Nimro did חליצה chalitzah to her. All right. Is that clear? You
got it? And then the same thing is in, that allows this
part to work and then the same thing is reversed. He does
חליצה, chalitzah, he does יבום, yibum, that's fine. But wait a minute,
maybe the one he's doing יבום yibum with, רחל, Rachel, maybe was
married to ראובן? Reuven? No problem, שמעון Shimon did חליצה. chalitzah. Okay,
so basically each half is what we saw before, but the presence
of the חליצה chalitzah from the other half just frees her up.
Yes. This is the יבום yibum isotope paradigm. Thank you. So now
let's just finish this משנה. mishnah. Okay, קדמו שנים וחלצו, Kadmu shnayim
vechiltzu, לא ייבמו השנים, lo yeyavemu hashnayim, אלא אחד חולץ ואחד מייבם.
ela echad choletz v'echad meyavem. Now let's say you had two חליצות
chalitzos done from one side of the family. Okay, you had חליצה
chalitzah and חליצה. chalitzah. Fine. So now they're both out of the
picture. Okay, they're out of the picture. So it says, קדמו שנים
וחלצו, Kadmu shnayim vechiltzu, what does it say? So לא ייבמו השנים.
lo yeyavemu hashnayim. Don't both do יבום. yibum. Of course don't both
do יבום yibum because once these guys both do חליצה, chalitzah, they're
out of the picture. We're back to where we were before. ראובן
Reuven dies, don't both do יבום. yibum. The first guy who does
יבום yibum will be אחות זקוקתו, achis zekukaso, right? You're having sex
with a woman who might be the sister of the woman you
really have to do יבום yibum with. So when these get out
of the picture, we're back to the idea they both shouldn't do
יבום. yibum. One does חליצה chalitzah and one does יבום. yibum. However,
קדמו וכנסו, Kadmu vechanasu, אין מוציאין מידם. ein motzi'in miyadam. If they
both did יבום, yibum, they're allowed to stay married because once even
though if שמעון Shimon did יבום yibum with רחל, Rachel, it might
have been אחות זקוקתו, achis zekukaso, right? But once לוי Levi did
יבום yibum with לאה, Leah, רחל Rachel stops being related to the
זקוק, zakuk, I'm sorry, once לוי Levi did יבום yibum with לאה,
Leah, לאה Leah stops having any relationship with שמעון Shimon and he
can stay therefore married to רחל. Rachel. Okay, so it's all basically
the same idea except we're introducing another family down here to complicate
it. But once you remove this other family, we're back to the
idea that either you do חליצה, chalitzah, you're supposed to do חליצה
chalitzah and יבום. yibum. If you did יבום yibum first, that you
shouldn't have done because that might be אחות זקוקתו, achis zekukaso, but
once יבום yibum was done with the sister, with לאה, Leah, that
freed, that got לאה Leah out of the picture for שמעון Shimon
and he can continue to be married to רחל. Rachel. Okay, I
hope you all got that. Nice, that was great.